<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[For the Love of Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://hpetrow.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hpetrow.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-16T08:20:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://hpetrow.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Heather Petrow]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Am I Just an Instance?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpetrow.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/am-i-just-an-instance/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-16T07:41:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpetrow.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/am-i-just-an-instance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Object-oriented programming is an elegant design pattern due to its fundamental
abstraction of logic, and the ability to encapsulate data storage and transfer
in an organized system of properties and behavior. The oo model is so beautiful
and logical because it is dependant on relationships and communication, which
mirrors some of the most powerful and efficient systems in nature, from ant
colonies to neural networks. Classes can share the same data in the form of
class methods and class variables, but instances may have unique values and
behavior through instance methods and variables. Ie. We are all humans,
@@alive = true, trying to make sense of @@life_the_universe_and_everything = 42,
but are also different and unique individuals, with different @characteristics
and @experiences.</p>

<p>In particular, object-oriented programming in Ruby is empowering and liberating,
because of the lack of authoritarian restriction sometimes present in other
languages. As a person who is loosely devout to categorization and right angles,
oop in Ruby can seem at first like the wild west of coding. Coming from some
Java experience, which tends to be strongly typed, Ruby seems at first like an
irresponsible caretaker, letting variables hang around with whomever they
choose. However, it is this freedom that enables dynamic assignment and
interaction. The programmer is liberated from fussing over types and
typecasting, focusing rather upon functionality and logical relationships. Ruby
trusts the human, because it was written for the human, and doesn&rsquo;t impose
stringent rules to chastise at every incompatible type.</p>

<p>Like many others here at Flatiron, there was a time when programming was the
last thing I would have imagined myself doing. Coding always seemed like a
mysterious realm where pedantic geniuses were permanantly hunched over machines,
typing endless lines of crytic mathematical prescience. It was such an internal
upheaval to discover this love for coding that it is still sometimes difficult
to believe. Yet I need only to call upon self.loves_to_code #=> true, to verify
its validity. Now, I can hardly imagine my life without code. I suppose fate is
a clever (rubyist) programmer.</p>

<p>It occurs to me that learning to let ourselves love something new, such as
coding, may be more difficult the more strongly we type our properties. We may
resist assigning our attributes to unknown types, because we have defined
ourselves and our variables so strictly. My Java self would have triggered an
onslaught of compile-time errors at any attempt to assign this type of
Programmer. Conversely, my Ruby self allows me to embrace new ideas and
experiences, and yet, still remain the same self. I have come to deeply
appreciate the Ruby language, because it allows me to focus on expression and
meaning, to view the self as a whole, rather than belaboring the mechanics of
every thought and decision.</p>

<p>So, if, in moments of existential crisis, I can hardly recognize this version of
self, with instance variables so different from the self that existed not so
very long ago, perhaps there is some solace in believing that perhaps I am
merely an instance with a particular object identity, taking up some
insignificant, temporal space in memory. My properties may have changed, but my
identity has not. In moments of doubt, I&rsquo;ll call upon my methods.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Post on Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpetrow.github.io/blog/2015/06/14/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-14T16:05:56-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpetrow.github.io/blog/2015/06/14/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
